<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-tldr-sutld-ps-01" ipr="trust200902"
     obsoletes="" updates="">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Special-use Names Problem">Special Use Names Problem
    Statement</title>

    <author fullname="Ted Lemon" initials="T" surname="Lemon">
      <organization>Nominum, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>800 Bridge Parkway</street>

          <city>Redwood City</city>

          <region>California</region>

          <country>United States of America</country>

          <code>94065</code>
        </postal>

        <phone>+1 650 381 6000</phone>

        <email>ted.lemon@nominum.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Ralph Droms" initials="R" surname="Droms">
      <organization>Cisco, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <email>rdroms.ietf@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Warren Kumari" initials="W." surname="Kumari">
      <organization>Google</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1600 Amphitheatre Parkway</street>

          <city>Mountain View, CA</city>

          <code>94043</code>

          <country>US</country>
        </postal>

        <email>warren@kumari.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="20" month="June" year="2016"/>

    <abstract>
      <t>The Special-Use Domain Names registration policy in RFC 6761 has been
      shown through experience to present unanticipated challenges. This memo
      explores current IETF and non-IETF publications relating on special-use
      domain names, briefly describes the history of domain names, and
      enumerates some problems that have come up in connection with the
      Special-Use Domain Names allocation process specifically as it related
      to top-level domains.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>At the time of this writing, the IETF has recently been asked to
      allocate several new special-use top-level names. In evaluating the
      process for additional special-use-top-level names as documented in
      <xref target="RFC6761">Special-Use Domain Names</xref>, the IETF
      encountered several different sorts of issues. Because of this, the IETF
      has decided to investigate the problem and decide if and how the RFC
      6761 process can be improved, or whether it should be deprecated.</t>

      <t>In order to investigate this question, this document attempts first
      to document existing practice, then to briefly review the history of
      domain names, and finally to describe the set of problems that exist as
      reported by various IETF participants with experience in the various
      aspects of the problem.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Terminology">
      <t>For the sake of brevity this document uses a number of abbreviations.
      These are expanded here: <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Internet Name">A name which serves as input to a host's
          ordinary name resolution process, for example 'EXAMPLE.ORG'.</t>

          <t hangText="SUIN">Special Use Internet Name</t>

          <t hangText="SUTLIN">Special-Use Top-Level Internet Name</t>

          <t hangText="IANA">Internet Assigned Numbers Authority</t>

          <t hangText="ICANN">Internet Corporation for Assigned Names and
          Numbers</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section title="Existing Practice Regarding SUINs">
      <t>There are three primary and numerous secondary documents to consider
      when thinking about the Special-Use Internet Names process.</t>

      <section title="Primary SUIN Documents">
        <t>The primary documents are considered primary because they directly
        address the IETF's past thoughts on this topic in a general way, and
        also because they describe what the IETF does in practice. Only one of
        these documents is an IETF consensus document.</t>

        <section title="IAB Technical Comment on the Unique DNS Root">
          <t><xref target="RFC2826">This document</xref> is not an IETF
          consensus document, and appears to have been written to address a
          different problem than the SUIN problem. However, it speaks directly
          to several of the key issues that must be considered, and of course
          coming as it does from the IAB, it is rightly given with a great
          deal of authority despite not being an IETF consensus document.</t>

          <t>This document should be considered required reading for IETF
          participants who wish to express an informed opinion on the topic of
          SUINs. The main points that appear relevant to the specal use names
          problem are: <list style="symbols">
              <t>The Internet requires a globally unique namespace</t>

              <t>Private networks may operate private namespaces, but still
              require that names in the public namespace be globally
              unique.</t>

              <t>The <xref target="RFC1035">Domain Name System</xref> is not
              the only protocol that may be used for resolving domain
              names.</t>

              <t>Users cannot be assumed to know how to distinguish between
              symbols that have local meaning and symbols that have global
              meaning. Users may therefore share symbols that incorporate
              domain names with no global meaning (for example, a URL of
              'http://mysite.example.corp', where 'example.corp' is a domain
              allocated privately and informally as described in <xref
              target="SDO-ICANN-COLL"/>). Such symbols might refer to the
              object the user intends to share within that user's context, but
              either refer to some other object any recipient's context, or
              might not refer to any object at all in a recipient's context.
              The effect of this is that the user's intended communication
              will not be able to be understood by the recipients of the
              communication. This same problem can also occur simply because a
              single user copies a name from one context in which it has one
              meaning, into a different context in which it has a different
              meaning&mdash; for example copying a '.onion' internet name out
              of a TOR browser, where it has meaning, and pasting this name
              into an ssh client that doesn't support connecting over TOR.
              [TODO: Consider "labels" instead of "symbols".]</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>To boil this down even further, we can take the following advice
          from this document: <list style="symbols">
              <t>Domain names with unambiguous global meaning are preferable
              to domain names with local meaning which will be ambiguous, but
              nevertheless both globally-meaningful and locally-special names
              are in use and must be supported.</t>

              <t>At the time of the writing of this document the IAB was of
              the opinion that there might well be more than one name
              resolution protocol used to resolve domain names.</t>
            </list></t>
        </section>

        <section title="Special-Use Domain Names">
          <t>The second important document is <xref target="RFC6761">
          Special-Use Domain Names</xref>. RFC6761 represents the current IETF
          consensus on designating and recording SUTLINs. The IETF has
          experienced problems with the designation process described in
          RFC6761; these concerns motivate this document. Again, familiarity
          with RFC6761 is a prerequisite for having an informed opinion on the
          topic of SUINs.</t>

          <t>RFC 6761 defines two aspects of SUINs: designating a domain name
          to have a special purpose and registering that special use in the
          Special-Use Domain Names registry. The designation process is
          defined in a single sentence (RFC6761, section 4):</t>

          <t><list style="empty">
              <t>If it is determined that special handling of a name is
              required in order to implement some desired new functionality,
              then an IETF "Standards Action" or "IESG Approval" specification
              [RFC5226] MUST be published describing the new
              functionality.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>This sentence implies that the designation be subject to the same
          open review and consensus process as used to produce and publish all
          other IETF specifications.</t>

          <t>The registration process is a purely mechanical process, in which
          the existence of the newly designated special use name is recorded,
          with a pointer to a section in the relevant specification document
          that defines the ways in which special handling is to be applied to
          the name.</t>

          <t>RFC6761 provided the explicit designation and inclusion in the
          Special-Use Names registry for '.local' and for a set of names that
          had been previously used or defined to have special uses before the
          publication of RFC6761.</t>

          <t>There are at least three important points to think of with
          respect to the RFC6761: <list style="symbols">
              <t>A special-use name may be a name that should be resolved
              using the DNS protocol with no special handling. An example of
              this is .ARPA.</t>

              <t>A special-use name may be a name that should be resolved
              using the DNS protocol, but requires special handling in the
              resolver.</t>

              <t>A special-use name may be a TLD like '.local' which acts as a
              signal to indicate that the local stub resolver should use a
              non-DNS protocol for name resolution.</t>

              <t>The current IETF consensus (from a process perspective, not
              necessarily from the perspective of what would be consensus if
              the IETF were to attempt to produce a new consensus document) is
              that both of these applications for special-use names are valid.
              [TODO: "Both" implies that there are only two applications; the
              above bullet points outline 3...]</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>It should be noted also that RFC6761 does not limit special-use
          names to TLDs. However, at present, all special-use names registered
          in the <xref target="SDO-IANA-SUDR"> IANA Special-Use Domain Names
          registry</xref> are either intended to be resolved using the DNS
          protocol, or are top-level domains, or both. That is, at present
          there is no protocol switch required by RFC6761 for names other than
          at the top level of the naming hierarchy.</t>

          <t>However, the obvious corollary to this is that at present,
          RFC6761 requires the use of a special label, '.LOCAL', to indicate
          to stub resolvers that mDNS<xref target="RFC6762"/> be used to
          resolve names under that label. [TODO: Not sure why this is
          considered a corollary?]</t>
        </section>

        <section title="MoU Concerning the Technical Work of the IANA">
          <t>There exists a Memorandum of Understanding<xref
          target="RFC2860"/> between the IETF and ICANN (Internet Corporation
          for Assigned Names and Numbers) which discusses how names and
          numbers will be managed through the IANA (Internet Assigned Numbers
          Authority). This document is important to the discussion of SUINs
          because, while it delegates authority for managing the Domain Name
          System Namespace generally to ICANN, it reserves to the IETF the
          authority that RFC 6761 formalizes: <list style="empty">
              <t>Note that (a) assignments of domain names for technical uses
              (such as domain names for inverse DNS lookup), (b) assignments
              of specialised address blocks (such as multicast or anycast
              blocks), and (c) experimental assignments are not considered to
              be policy issues, and shall remain subject to the provisions of
              this Section 4.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>To understand the context of Section 4 of the document, it should
          be noted that the above text is an addendum to the following text:
          <list style="empty">
              <t>Two particular assigned spaces present policy issues in
              addition to the technical considerations specified by the IETF:
              the assignment of domain names, and the assignment of IP address
              blocks. These policy issues are outside the scope of this
              MOU.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>The point here is that, in general, the assignment of names in
          the DNS root zone, and the management of the DNS namespace
          generally, is a function that is performed by ICANN. However, the
          MoU specifically exempts domain names assigned for technical use,
          and uses the example of 'IN-ADDR.ARPA' and 'IP6.ARPA' to illustrate.
          Both of these names are in the RFC 6761 registry.</t>

          <t>The point here is not to say what the implications of this
          statement in the MoU are, but rather to call the reader's attention
          to the existence of this statement.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Secondary documents relating to the SUTLIN question">
        <t>In addition to these documents, there are several others with which
        participants in this discussion should be familiar.</t>

        <section title="Multicast DNS">
          <t>Multicast DNS <xref target="RFC6762"/> defines the Multicast DNS
          protocol, which uses the '.LOCAL' SUTLIN. Section 3 describes the
          semantics of "multicast DNS names." It is of considerable historical
          importance to note that the -00 version of this document, an
          individual submission, was published in July of 2001. This version
          contains substantially the same text in section 3, and was discussed
          in the DNSEXT working group at IETF 51 in August of 2001<xref
          target="IETF-PRO-51"/>.</t>

          <t>The history of RFC 6762 is documented in substantial detail in
          Appendix H; some notable milestones include the initial proposal to
          replace Appletalk's NBP in July 1997, the chartering of the Zeroconf
          working group in September 1999, allocation of a multicast address
          for link-local name discovery in April of 2000. A companion
          requirements document, eventually published as <xref
          target="RFC6760"/> was first published in September of 2001.</t>

          <t>The point of mentioning these dates is so that discussions
          involving the time when the '.LOCAL' domain was first deployed, and
          the context in which it was deployed, may be properly informed.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="The .onion Special-Use TLD">
          <t><xref target="RFC7686">The .onion Special Use TLD</xref> is
          important because it is the most recent IETF action on the topic of
          SUTLINs; although it does not set new policy, the mere fact of its
          publication is worth thinking about.</t>

          <t>Two important points to consider about this document are that:
          <list style="symbols">
              <t>The IETF gained consensus to publish it</t>

              <t>The situation was somewhat forced, both by the fact of its
              unilateral allocation by the TOR project without following the
              RFC 6761 process, and <xref target="SDO-CABF-INT"> because a
              deadline had been set by the CA/Browser Forum</xref> after which
              all .onion PKI certificates would expire and no new certificates
              would be issued, unless the .onion SUTLIN were to be recognized
              by the IETF.</t>
            </list></t>
        </section>

        <section title="Locally Served DNS Zones">
          <t><xref target="RFC6303">Locally Served DNS Zones</xref> describes
          a particular use case for zones that exist by definition, and that
          are resolved using the DNS protocol, but that cannot have a global
          meaning, because the host IP addresses they reference are not
          unique. This applies to a variety of addresses, including <xref
          target="RFC1918"> Private IPv4 addresses</xref>, <xref
          target="RFC4193">Unique Local IPv6 Unicast Addresses</xref> (in
          which this practice was first described) and <xref
          target="RFC6598">IANA-Reserved IPv4 Prefix for Shared Address
          Space</xref>.</t>

          <t>This use case is distinct from the use-case for SUTLINs like
          '.local' and '.onion' in that the names are resolved using the DNS
          protocol, but shares the problem that such names cannot be assumed
          either to be unique or to be functional in all contexts for all
          internet-connected hosts.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Name Collision in the DNS">
          <t><xref target="SDO-ICANN-COLL">Name Collision in the DNS</xref> is
          a study commissioned by ICANN that attempts to characterize the
          potential risk to the Internet of creating a registration process
          for new top-level domains that would allow corporations and persons
          to, for a fee, request a delegation for a particular top-level
          domain. The document concludes that such allocations do present some
          risks, and mentions three specific top-level internet names,
          '.home', '.corp' and '.mail', that present sufficient risk that they
          must never be allocated by ICANN.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Discovery of the IPv6 Prefix Used for IPv6 Address Synthesis">
          <t><xref target="RFC7050">Discovery of the IPv6 Prefix Used for IPv6
          Address Synthesis</xref> is an example of a document that
          successfully used the RFC 6761 process to designate '.ipv4only.arpa'
          as a special-use name; in this case the process worked smoothly and
          without controversy.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Additional Reserved Top Level Domains">
          <t><xref target="I-D.chapin-additional-reserved-tlds"> Additional
          Reserved Top Level Domains</xref> is an example of a document that
          attempted to reserve several TLDs identified by ICANN as
          particularly at risk for collision as special-use domain names with
          no documented use. This attempt failed, for better or for worse.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Observations based on reading these documents">
        <t>Readers of this memo are strongly encouraged to familiarize
        themselves with the documents referenced above and to draw their own
        conclusions. However, for the sake of beginning the discussion, some
        observations are presented here.</t>

        <t>Neither RFC 6761 nor RFC 7686 require any kind of delegation for
        '.onion' or '.local'. At least in the case of '.onion', it might be
        better if there were a delegation in order to limit the scope of
        leakage of '.onion' queries made to resolvers that do not know how to
        resolve '.onion' names. However, the DNS protocol does not currently
        provide a mechanism for signaling that a particular name is not
        intended to be resolved using the DNS protocol, and it might be better
        to address that problem before defining a delegation for '.onion'.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="History">
      <t>Newcomers to the problem of resolving domain names may be under the
      mistaken impression that the DNS sprang, like the greek legend of
      Athena, directly from Paul Mockapetris' forehead. This is not the case.
      At the time of the writing of the IAB technical document, memories would
      have been fresh of the evolutionary process that led to the DNS'
      dominance as a protocol for domain name resolution.</t>

      <t>In fact, in the early days of the Internet, hostnames were resolved
      using a text file, HOSTS.TXT, which was maintained by a central
      authority, the Network Information Center, and distributed to all hosts
      on the internet using the <xref target="RFC0959">File Transfer Protocol
      (FTP)</xref>. The inefficiency of this process is cited as a reason for
      the development of <xref target="RFC1034">the DNS</xref> in 1983.</t>

      <t>However, the transition from HOSTS.TXT to the DNS was not smooth. For
      example, <xref target="CORP-SUN-NIS">Sun Microsystems's Network
      Information System</xref>, at the time known as Yellow Pages, was an
      active competitor to the DNS, although it failed to provide a complete
      solution to the global naming problem.</t>

      <t>Most modern operating systems can still use the '/etc/hosts' file for
      name resolution. Many still have a name service switch that can be
      configured on the host to resolve some domains using NIS. Most have the
      capability to resolve names using mDNS by recognizing the special
      meaning of the '.local' SUTLIN.</t>

      <t>The Sun Microsystems model of having private domains within a
      corporate site, while supporting the global domain name system for
      off-site persisted even after the NIS protocol fell into disuse.
      Microsoft used to recommend that site administrators allocate a
      "private" top-level domain for internal use, and this practice was very
      much a part of the zeitgeist at the time. This attitude is the root of
      the widespread practice of simply picking an unused top-level domain and
      using it for experimental purposes, which persists even at the time of
      writing of this memo.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Problems with Special-Use TLDs and Their Allocation">
      <t>RFC 6761 serves two purposes. First, it enumerates a set of domain
      names that require special treatment either by stub resolvers or by
      authority and caching name servers. Second, it establishes a registry
      for future such names, and in section 5 it describes considerations for
      deciding when such names should be allocated. This has been a success in
      the sense that this registry now exists and has been used, but the
      stated considerations don't work for all use cases, and there are
      questions about whether this is even the right approach. This section
      attempts to enumerate these problems in no deliberate order.</t>

      <section title="Purity of Domain Name Architecture Problem">
        <t>There is some question as to whether special-use TLDs may violate
        the Domain Name System Architecture. Much discussion has centered
        around three aspects of this question. There is, of course, no
        document titled "The Domain Name System Architecture," so we have to
        rely on the various documents referenced earlier to consider this
        question. RFC2826 seems to speak most directly to it.</t>

        <section title="Are Domain Names DNS Names?">
          <t>The first of the three aspects of the purity question is whether
          domain names are specific to the DNS protocol. RFC2826 appears to
          state unequivocally that they are not. However, many people have
          expressed the opinion that they are. This is a question that may
          need to be explored further through the IETF process.</t>

          <t>At present, there are three obvious exceptions to the use of the
          DNS protocol to resolve domain names: '.onion', '.local' and any
          name that appears in /etc/hosts or the equivalent. If indeed DNS is
          the only protocol to be used for resolving domain names, these use
          cases would have to be deprecated.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Does Every Domain Name Have The Same Meaning Everywhere?">
          <t>The second aspect of the purity question is the question of
          whether at any particular time, every domain name refers to the same
          entity regardless of where the query comes from.</t>

          <t>It has been stated by various participants in this discussion
          that, in fact, they do. RFC2862 seems to make a very strong case
          that to the extent possible they should be, but does not go so far
          as to insist that in all cases they must be. '.onion' actually
          should exhibit this property. However, '.local' does not.</t>

          <t>There are other examples of domain names that cannot be assumed
          to have the same meaning everywhere. For example, it is not
          unreasonable for a site that uses RFC1918 addresses to populate the
          DNS reverse lookup tree for their copy of the address space.
          Fortunately, names of this sort are rarely seen by users who do not
          understand their limited scope of applicability, making this
          exception a violation in fact but not in spirit of this
          principle.</t>

          <t>There is the additional case of names that refer to different IP
          addresses depending on the location of the host that originates the
          query. Although at first glance this appears to be an example of the
          problem, it actually is not, because the entity to which the name
          refers is the same entity, cached in different locations.</t>

          <t>Something similar can be said about domain names that refer to
          objects that may be harmful to devices that access them. A caching
          resolver may refuse to answer queries for such names, or may return
          answers that differ from the answer that the name server
          authoritative for that name is returning. Again, although this seems
          like an exception, it probably is not, because in this case the user
          who is attempting to share a reference to the entity is either
          malicious or has been duped, and in either case a failure to
          successfully share the entity is, presumably, an intended outcome
          from the perspective of the recipient of the reference.</t>

          <t>If it were to be determined that the principle expressed in RFC
          2862 that domain names should always refer to the same object is too
          weak, this would necessitate changing the operational model of
          Multicast DNS, and would render the use of names derived from
          non-unique IP addresses at least in principle out of bounds.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Protocol Switch Problem">
          <t>The third of the three aspects of the purity question is the
          problem that if we do not resolve all domains using the same
          protocol, there has to be a mechanism for determining which protocol
          to use to resolve any particular name. If the names that must be
          resolved using different protocols all exist directly under the root
          of the namespace, this determination is relatively simple, but
          clearly using the DNS protocol for all queries would be simpler.</t>

          <t>An additional consideration about this aspect of the question is
          whether future resolver implementations should be required to engage
          in any behavior to determine whether a particular TLD for which they
          have no special information is a SUTLIN or a normal TLD. Also, since
          there can be privacy implications to special-use TLD queries, does
          it make sense to require that all resolvers take some action to test
          the special-use-ness of each TLD for which they are asked to resolve
          queries before sending the complete query out over the wire using
          the DNS Protocol.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Land Rush Problem">
        <t>The land rush problem refers to the concern that has been expressed
        that if the IETF is seen to be able to allocate TLDs outside of the
        ICANN process, persons and entities who might otherwise apply to ICANN
        for the use of a particular TLD might instead apply to the IETF. The
        concern is that this could overwhelm the IESG's ability to process
        these, particularly since one option for SUTLIN allocation is "IESG
        Approval."</t>

        <t>It is therefore important to clarify what sorts of use cases make
        sense for both the "Standards Action" and "IESG Approval." It seems
        clear that if there are good use cases for SUTLINs, they would be in
        the production of standards that the IETF considers important, not for
        the purpose of assigning domains for normal delegation in the DNS.</t>

        <t>It is not the case that all special-use TLDs can be expected to be
        non-DNS names; for example, the Homenet Working Group is likely to
        propose the use of a special-use TLD for use on the homenet in cases
        where the homenet does not have its own globally unique name
        allocated. This would nevertheless be resolved in the same way as an
        RFC1918 reverse query, by sending a query to the local resolver using
        the DNS protocol.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="IESG Getting Sued Problem">
        <t>An additional serious problem in allocating SUTLINs is that it
        exposes the IETF to the risk of lawsuits from interested parties.
        While this is obviously a real risk, it is not special to the SUTLIN
        problem--the IETF is always potentially at risk of being sued.
        However, ICANN has developed a process for evaluating the issues that
        might arise with respect to the allocation of a TLD. The IETF could,
        in principle, take advantage of this evaluation process through the
        agency of the IANA, which at present is a function managed by
        ICANN.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Warranted Allocation Problem">
        <t>The issue here is similar to the Land Rush problem: the IETF is
        being asked to evaluate whether a particular protocol use of a SUTLIN
        justifies the permanent sacrifice of that name in the registry, and
        the appearance of that name in the name service protocol switches of
        various stub resolver implementations.</t>

        <t>Several things could be considered here. One is that there exist
        processes for other registries where names are temporarily reserved;
        if the protocol for which they were reserved turns out to be <xref
        target="RFC5218">a success</xref>, then the reservation can be made
        permanent. If not, it's deleted from the registry.</t>

        <t>A corrollary to this is that if a protocol is not a success, it
        likely will not be implemented in the protocol switches of mainstream
        host operating systems. This mitigates this aspect of the damage that
        would be caused by a mistake here.</t>

        <t>The final point to be made about this concern is that it is not at
        all unique to SUTLINs. The IETF frequently produces protocols that do
        not turn out to be successes by the criteria set forth in RFC5218.
        Each of these protocol efforts began with the IETF chartering process,
        the working group consensus process, and the IETF and IESG review
        processes. These processes do not prevent unsuccessful protocols from
        being produced, but they do very much limit the rate at which they are
        produced, and, it is to be hoped, improve the ratio of successes to
        failures. There is no reason to think that this particular IANA
        registry is special in this regard, nor to treat it specially simply
        because we are aware of this problem.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Experimental Squatting Problem">
        <t>One of the problems with SUTLINs is that various protocol
        development efforts find it convenient to use SUTLINs as a name
        service protocol switch precisely because such switches exist in most
        popular operating systems. So a project will allocate a name without
        going through the RFC6761 process, and then later on will want that
        allocation to be made permanent. Several organizations that have
        actually done this have indicated that they looked for a process they
        could use to get a name, found RFC6761, realized it wouldn't work for
        them, found nothing else, and then just unilaterally allocated the
        name.</t>

        <t>Precisely because of the principle stated in RFC 2826, that names
        that do not consistently refer to the same object create problems for
        end users, this creates pressure once use of the protocol becomes
        somewhat widespread, yet not widespread enough or strategic enough to
        justify allocation by the IETF, for the organization that squatted on
        the name to try to get the IETF to formalize the allocation.</t>

        <t>Solutions have been proposed for this problem. There already exists
        a TLD, '.test', under which such an allocation could in principle be
        made, but no RFC exists recommending this practice. Furthermore,
        RFC6761 recommends resolving .test using the DNS, so this isn't
        exactly the right thing for a name service protocol switch.</t>

        <t>A draft exists to allocate a '.alt' TLD to address this need. The
        draft as currently written attempts to solve the whole SUTLIN problem,
        but fails to do so. This draft could easily be restricted to simply
        defining a SUTLIN under which new non-DNS resolution strategies could
        be tested, and this would likely resolve the bulk of the experimental
        squatting problems that might come up in the future. [TODO:
        Revise]</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Insecure Delegation Problem">
        <t>At present RFC6761 doesn't give specific advice about what
        delegation, if any, should appear for newly registered SUTLINs. It may
        be worthwhile to make a default recommendation for this. This may tie
        in with the idea that SUTLINs should have some signal in the DNS that
        tells the resolver not to try to use DNS to resolve names under that
        TLD, even if they don't have an alternative protocol to try.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="The Who's In Charge of the Root Problem">
        <t>The last but not least problem is that RFC6761 assumes that the
        IETF has change control over the set of names that appear in the root
        zone. The sense in which the IETF is in a position to allocate names
        in the root zone is complicated. If the outcome of this process is
        that the IETF continues to make allocations of domain names,
        particularly in the root zone, it is likely that it will be necessary
        to establish some clarity about the basis on which this is done.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Contributors">
      <t>This document came about as a result of conversations that occurred
      the weekend before IETF 95 in the lobby. Stuart Cheshire, Mark Andrews,
      David Conrad, Paul Ebersman and Aaron Falk all made helpful and
      insightful observations or patiently answered questions. This should not
      be taken as an indication that any of these folks actually agree with
      what the document says, but their generosity with time and thought are
      appreciated in any case. Ralph started out as an innocent bystander, but
      discussion with him was the key motivating factor in the writing of this
      document, and he agreed to co-author it without too much arm-twisting.
      And this document owes a great deal to Ed Lewis' excellent work on <xref
      target="I-D.lewis-domain-names">what a "domain name" is</xref>.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.0959" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.1034" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.1035" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.1918" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2826" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2860" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4193" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5218" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6303" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6598" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6760" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6761" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6762" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6763" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7050" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7686" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.chapin-additional-reserved-tlds" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.lewis-domain-names" ?>

      <reference anchor="SDO-CABF-INT"
                 target="https://www.digicert.com/internal-names.htm">
        <front>
          <title>Guidance on the Deprecation of Internal Server Names and
          Reserved IP Addresses</title>

          <author>
            <organization>CA/Browser Forum</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="June" year="2012"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="SDO-ICANN-COLL"
                 target="https://www.icann.org/en/system/files/files/name-collision-02aug13-en.pdf">
        <front>
          <title>Name Collisions in the DNS</title>

          <author>
            <organization>Interisle Consulting Group, LLC</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="August" year="2013"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="SDO-IANA-SUDR"
                 target="http://www.iana.org/assignments/special-use-domain-names/special-use-domain-names.xhtml">
        <front>
          <title>Special-Use Domain Names registry</title>

          <author>
            <organization>Internet Assigned Numbers Authority</organization>
          </author>

          <date day="27" month="October" year="2015"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="CORP-SUN-NIS">
        <front>
          <title>System and Network Administration</title>

          <author>
            <organization>Sun Microsystems</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="March" year="1990"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="IETF-PRO-51"
                 target="http://www.ietf.org/proceedings/51/51-45.htm#TopOfPage">
        <front>
          <title>Proceedings of the 51st IETF</title>

          <author>
            <organization>Internet Engineering Task Force</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="August" year="2001"/>
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
