<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc comments="yes" ?>
<?rfc inline="yes" ?>
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-ietf-dnsop-sutld-ps-07" ipr="trust200902"
     obsoletes="" updates="">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Special-Use Domain Names Problem">Special-Use Domain Names
    Problem Statement</title>

    <author fullname="Ted Lemon" initials="T" surname="Lemon">
      <organization>Nominum, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>800 Bridge Parkway</street>

          <city>Redwood City</city>

          <region>California</region>

          <country>United States of America</country>

          <code>94065</code>
        </postal>

        <phone>+1 650 381 6000</phone>

        <email>ted.lemon@nominum.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Ralph Droms" initials="R" surname="Droms">
      <organization/>

      <address>
        <email>rdroms.ietf@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Warren Kumari" initials="W." surname="Kumari">
      <organization>Google</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1600 Amphitheatre Parkway</street>

          <city>Mountain View, CA</city>

          <code>94043</code>

          <country>US</country>
        </postal>

        <email>warren@kumari.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="July" year="2017"/>

    <abstract>
      <t>The Special-Use Domain Names IANA registry policy defined in RFC 6761
      has been shown through experience to present unanticipated challenges.
      This memo presents a list, intended to be comprehensive, of the problems
      that have been identified. In addition it reviews the history of Domain
      Names and summarizes current IETF publications and some publications
      from other organizations relating to Special-Use Domain Names.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>One of the key services required to use the Internet is name
      resolution. Name resolution is the process of translating a symbolic
      name into some object or set of objects to which the name refers, most
      typically one or more IP addresses. These names are often referred to as
      Domain Names. When reading this document, care must be taken to not
      assume that the term Domain Name implies the use of the <xref
      target="RFC1034">Domain Name System</xref> for resolving these names. An
      excellent presentation on this topic can be found in <xref
      target="I-D.lewis-domain-names">Domain Names</xref>.</t>

      <t><xref target="RFC6761">Special-Use Domain Names</xref> created <xref
      target="SDO-IANA-SUDR">an IANA registry for Special-Use Domain
      Names</xref>, defined policies for adding to the registry, and made some
      suggestions about how those policies might be implemented. Since the
      publication of RFC 6761, the IETF has been asked to designate several
      new Special-Use Domain Names in this registry. During the evaluation
      process for these Special-Use Domain Names, the IETF encountered several
      different sorts of issues. Because of this, the IETF has decided to
      investigate the problem and decide if and how the RFC 6761 process can
      be improved, or whether it should be deprecated. The IETF DSNOP working
      group charter was extended to include conducting a review of the process
      for adding names to the registry that is defined in RFC 6761. This
      document is a product of that review.</t>

      <t>Based on current ICANN and IETF practice, including RFC 6761, there
      are several different types of names in the root of the Domain
      Namespace: <list style="symbols">
          <t>Reserved by the IETF for technical purposes</t>

          <t>Assigned by ICANN to the public DNS root; some names reserved by
          the IETF for technical purposes may appear in the Global DNS root
          for reasons pertaining to the operation of the DNS</t>

          <t>ICANN Reserved Names; names that may not be applied for as TLDs
          (see <xref target="SDO-ICANN-DAG"/>, Section 2.2.1.2.1, Reserved
          Names, Section 2.2.1.4.1, Treatment of Country or Territory Names,
          et al.)</t>

          <t>Used by other organizations without following established
          processes</t>

          <t>Names that are unused and are available for assignment to one of
          the previous categories</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>This document presents a list, derived from a variety of sources
      including discussion in the IETF dnsop WG, of the problems associated
      with the assignment of Special-Use Domain Names. The list is intended to
      be an unfiltered compilation of issues. In support of its analysis of
      the particular set of issues described here, the document also includes
      descriptions of existing practice as it relates to the use of domain
      names, a brief history of domain names, and some observations by various
      IETF participants who have experience with various aspects of the
      current situation.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Terminology">
      <t>This document uses the terminology from <xref target="RFC7719">RFC
      7719</xref>. Other terms used in this document are defined here: <list
          style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Domain Name">This document uses the term "Domain Name"
          as defined in section 2 of <xref target="RFC7719">RFC
          7719</xref>.</t>

          <t hangText="Domain Namespace">The set of all possible Domain
          Names.</t>

          <t hangText="Special-Use Domain Name">A Domain Name listed in the
          Special-Use Domain Names registry <xref
          target="SDO-IANA-SUDR"/>.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>For the sake of brevity this document uses some abbreviations, which
      are expanded here: <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="IANA">Internet Assigned Numbers Authority</t>

          <t hangText="ICANN">Internet Corporation for Assigned Names and
          Numbers</t>

          <t hangText="TLD">Top-Level Domain, as defined in section 2 of <xref
          target="RFC7719">RFC 7719</xref></t>

          <t hangText="gTLD">Generic Top-Level Domain (see section 2 of <xref
          target="RFC2352">RFC 2352</xref>)</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section title="Problems associated with Special-Use Domain Names">
      <t>This section presents a list of problems that have been identified
      with respect to the assignment of Special-Use Domain Names. Solutions to
      these problems, including their costs or tradeoffs, are out of scope for
      this document. They will be covered in a separate document. New problems
      that might be created in the process of solving problems described in
      this document are also out of scope: these problems are expected to be
      addressed in the process of evaluating potential solutions.</t>

      <t>Special-Use Domain Names exist to solve a variety of problems. This
      document has two goals: enumerate all of the problems that have been
      identified to which Special-Use Domain Names are a solution and
      enumerate all of the problems that have been raised in the process of
      trying to use RFC 6761 as it was intended. As some of those problems may
      fall into both categories, this document makes no attempt to categorize
      the problems.</t>

      <t>There is a broad diversity of opinion about this set of problems. Not
      every participant agrees that each of the problems enumerated in this
      document is actually a problem. This document takes no position on the
      relative validity of the various problems that have been enumerated, nor
      on the organization responsible for addressing each individual problem,
      if it is to be addressed. The sole purposes of the document are to
      enumerate those problems, provide the reader with context for thinking
      about them and provide a context for future discussion of solutions,
      regardless of whether such solutions may be work for IETF, ICANN, IANA
      or some other group.</t>

      <t>This is the list of problems. This is not an ordered list, it is
      numbered merely to facilitate referencing specific problems: <list
          style="numbers">
          <t>Although the IETF and ICANN have a liaison relationship through
          which special-use allocations can be discussed, there exists no
          formal process for coordinating these allocations (see <xref
          target="MoU"/>). The lack of coordination complicates the management
          of the root of the Domain Namespace and <xref
          target="SDO-ICANN-SAC090"> could lead to conflicts in name
          assignments </xref>.</t>

          <t>There is no explicit scoping as to what can constitute a <xref
          target="RFC2860">"technical use"</xref> and what cannot, and there
          is also no consensus within the IETF as to what this term means.</t>

          <t>Not all developers of protocols on the internet agree that
          authority over the entire Domain Namespace should reside solely with
          the IETF and ICANN.</t>

          <t>Although IETF and ICANN nominally have authority over this
          namespace, neither organization can enforce that authority over any
          third party who wants to just start using a subset of the namespace.
          Such parties may observe that the IETF has never asserted control or
          authority over what protocols are "allowed" on the internet, and
          that the principle of "permissionless innovation" suggests there
          should be a way for people to include new uses of domain names in
          new protocols and applications.</t>

          <t>Organizations do in fact sometimes use subsets of the Domain
          Namespace without following established processes. Reasons a third
          party might do this include: <list style="numbers">
              <t>Unaware that a process exists for assigning such names</t>

              <t>Intended use is covered by gTLD process <xref
              target="SDO-ICANN-DAG"/>, but no gTLD process is ongoing</t>

              <t>Intended use is covered by gTLD process, but the third party
              doesn't want to pay a fee</t>

              <t>Intended use is covered by some IETF process, but the third
              party doesn't want to follow the process</t>

              <t>Intended use is covered by ICANN or IETF process, but third
              party expects that the outcome will be refusal or non-action</t>

              <t>Unaware that a name intended to be used only locally may
              nevertheless leak</t>

              <t>Unaware that a name used locally with informal allocation may
              subsequently be allocated formally, creating operational
              problems</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>There is demand for more than one name resolution protocol for
          Domain Names. Domain Names contain no metadata to indicate which
          protocol to use to resolve them. Domain name resolution APIs do not
          provide a way to specify which protocol to use.</t>

          <t>When a Special-Use Domain Name is added to the Special-Use Domain
          Names registry, not all software that processes such names will
          understand the special use of that name. In many cases, name
          resolution software will use the Domain Name System for resolution
          of names not known to have a special use. Consequently, any such use
          will result in queries for Special-Use Domain Names being sent to
          Domain Name System authoritative servers. These queries may
          constitute an operational problem for operators of root zone
          authoritative name servers. These queries may also inadvertently
          reveal private information through the contents of the query, which
          is a privacy consideration.</t>

          <t>The RFC 6761 process is sufficiently uncertain that some protocol
          developers have assumed they could not get a name assigned; the
          process of assigning the first new name ('.local') using the RFC
          6761 process took more than ten years from beginning to end: longer
          by a factor of ten than any other part of the protocol development
          process (largely because this ten years included time to develop the
          process as well as use it). Other uses of the process have proceeded
          more smoothly, but there is a reasonably justified perception that
          using this process is likely to be slow and difficult, with an
          uncertain outcome.</t>

          <t>There is strong resistance within the IETF to assigning Domain
          Names to resolution systems outside of the DNS, for a variety of
          reasons: <list style="numbers">
              <t>Requires a mechanism for identifying which of a set of
              resolution processes is required in order to resolve a
              particular name.</t>

              <t>Assertion of authority: there is a sense that the Domain
              Namespace is "owned" by the IETF or by ICANN, and so, if a name
              is claimed outside of that process, the person or entity that
              claimed that name should suffer some consequence that would,
              presumably, deter future circumvention of the official
              process.</t>

              <t>More than one name resolution protocol is bad, in the sense
              that a single protocol is less complicated to implement and
              deploy.</t>

              <t>The semantics of alternative resolution protocols may differ
              from the DNS protocol; DNS has the concept of RRtypes; other
              protocols may not support RRtypes, or may support some entirely
              different data structuring mechanism.</t>

              <t>If there is an IETF process through which a TLD can be
              assigned at zero cost other than time, this process will be used
              as an alternative to the more costly process of getting the name
              registered through ICANN.</t>

              <t>A name might be assigned for a particular purpose when a more
              general use of the name would be more beneficial.</t>

              <t>If the IETF assigns a name that some third party or parties
              believes belongs to them in some way, the IETF could become
              embroiled in an expensive dispute with those parties.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>If there were no process for assigning names for technical use
          through the IETF, there is a concern that protocols that require
          such names would not be able to get them.</t>

          <t>In some cases where the IETF has made assignments through the RFC
          6761 process, technical mistakes have been made due to
          misunderstandings as to the actual process that RFC 6761 specifies
          (e.g., treating the list of suggested considerations for assigning a
          name as a set of requirements all of which must be met). In other
          cases, the IETF has made de facto assignments of Special-Use Domain
          Names without following the RFC 6761 process.</t>

          <t>There are several Domain Name TLDs that are in use without due
          process for a variety of purposes. The status of these names need to
          be clarified and recorded to avoid future disputes about their use
          <xref target="SDO-ICANN-COLL"/>.</t>

          <t>In principle, the RFC 6761 process could be used to document the
          existence of Domain Names that are not safe to assign, and provide
          information on how those names are used in practice. However,
          attempts to use RFC 6761 to accomplish this documentation have not
          been successful (for example, see "Additional Reserved Top Level
          Domains <xref target="I-D.chapin-additional-reserved-tlds"/> and
          <xref target="addl-tlds"/>). One side effect of the lack of
          documentation is that any mitigation effect on the root name servers
          or on privacy considerations has been missed.</t>

          <t>A Domain Name can be identified as either a DNS name by placing
          it in the DNS zone(s) or as a Special-Use Domain Name by adding it
          to the IANA registry. Some names are in both places; for example,
          some locally served zone names are in DNS zones and documented in
          the Special-Use Domain Names registry. At present, the only way a
          Domain Name can be added to the Special-Use Domain Name registry is
          for the IETF to take responsibility for the name and designate it
          for "technical use". There are other potential uses for Domain Names
          that should be recorded in the registry, but for which the IETF
          should not take responsibility.</t>

          <t>The IETF may in some cases see the need to document that a name
          is in use without claiming that the use of the name is the IETF's
          use of the name. No mechanism exists in the current registry to mark
          names in this way.</t>

          <t>There is no formal process during any of the review stages for a
          document in which a check is made to ensure that the document does
          not unintentionally violate IETF process for adding special-use
          domain names to the registry, as was the case, for example, in RFC
          7788 <xref target="RFC7788"/>.</t>

          <t>Use of the registry is inconsistent -- some Special-Use Domain
          Name RFCs specifically add registry entries, some don't; some
          specify how and whether special-use name delegations should be done,
          some don't.</t>

          <t>There exists no safe, non-process-violating mechanism for ad-hoc
          assignment of Special-Use Domain Names.</t>

          <t>It is generally assumed that protocols that need a Special-Use
          Domain Name need a mnemonic, single-label, human-readable
          Special-Use Domain Name, for use in user interfaces such as command
          lines or URL entry fields. While this assumption is correct in some
          cases, it is likely not correct in all cases; for example, in
          applications where the DNS name is never visible to a user.</t>

          <t>RFC 6761 uses the term "Domain Name" to describe the thing for
          which special uses are registered. This creates a great deal of
          confusion because some readers take "Domain Name" to imply the use
          of the DNS protocol.</t>

          <t>The use of DNSSEC with Special-Use Domain Names is an open issue.
          There is no consensus or guidance about how to use DNSSEC with
          various classes of Special-Use Domain Names. Considerations in the
          use of DNSSEC with Special-Use Domain Names include: <list
              style="numbers">
              <t>What class of Special-Use Domain Name is under consideration:
              non-DNS, locally served zone, other?</t>

              <t>Does the Special-Use Domain Name require a delegation in the
              root zone; if so, should that delegation be signed or not? If
              there is no delegation, then this will be treated by validating
              resolvers as a secure denial of existence for that zone. This
              would not be appropriate for a name being resolved using the DNS
              protocol.</t>

              <t>A process would be required through which the IETF can cause
              a delegation in the root zone to be instantiated.</t>

              <t>What are the recommended practices for using DNS with the
              specific Special-Use Domain Name?</t>
            </list></t>
        </list></t>

      <t>The problems we have stated here represent the current understanding
      of the authors of the document as to the complete set of problems that
      have been identified during discussion by the working group on this
      topic. The remainder of this document provides additional context that
      will be needed for reasoning about these problems.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Existing Practice Regarding Special-Use Domain Names">
      <t>There are three primary (see <xref target="su_pri_docs"/>) and
      numerous secondary (<xref target="su_sec_docs"/>) documents to consider
      when thinking about the Special-Use Domain Names process.</t>

      <t>How names are resolved is ambiguous, in the sense that some names are
      Special-Use Domain names that require special handling, and some names
      can be resolved using the DNS protocol with no special handling.</t>

      <t>The assignment of Internet Names is not under the sole control of any
      one organization. IETF has authority in some cases, but only with
      respect to "technical uses." ICANN at present is the designated
      administrator of the root zone, but generally not of zones other than
      the root zone. Neither of these authorities can in any practical sense
      exclude the practice of ad-hoc use of names. Unauthorized use of domain
      names can be accomplished by any entity that has control over one or
      more name servers or resolvers, in the context of any hosts and services
      that entity operates. It can also be accomplished by authors of software
      who decide that a Special-Use Domain Name is the right way to indicate
      the use of an alternate resolution mechanism.</t>

      <section anchor="su_pri_docs"
               title="Primary Special-Use Domain Name Documents">
        <t>The primary documents are considered primary because they directly
        address the IETF's past thoughts on this topic in a general way, and
        also because they describe what the IETF does in practice.</t>

        <section title="IAB Technical Comment on the Unique DNS Root">
          <t><xref target="RFC2826">This document</xref> is not an IETF
          consensus document, and appears to have been written to address a
          different problem than the Special-Use Domain Name problem. However,
          it speaks directly to several of the key issues that must be
          considered, and, coming as it does from the IAB, it is rightly
          treated as having significant authority despite not being an IETF
          consensus document.</t>

          <t>This document should be considered required reading for IETF
          participants who wish to express an informed opinion on the topic of
          Special-Use Domain Names. The main points that appear relevant to
          the Special-Use Domain Names problem are: <list style="symbols">
              <t>The Internet requires a globally unique namespace: a
              namespace in which any given name refers to the same information
              (has the same meaning) no matter who requests that information
              and no matter from which specific name server they request
              it.</t>

              <t>Private networks may operate private namespaces, with names
              that have meanings only locally (within the private network) but
              still require that names in the public namespace be globally
              unique.</t>

              <t>The <xref target="RFC1035">Domain Name System</xref> is not
              the only protocol that may be used for resolving domain
              names.</t>

              <t>Users cannot be assumed to know how to distinguish between
              symbolic references that have local meaning and references that
              have global meaning. Users may therefore share references that
              incorporate Domain Names with no global meaning (for example, a
              URL of 'http://mysite.example.corp', where 'example.corp' is a
              domain used privately and informally as described in <xref
              target="SDO-ICANN-COLL"/>).</t>

              <t>Such references might refer to the object the user intends to
              share within that user's context, but either refer to some other
              object any recipient's context, or might not refer to any object
              at all in a recipient's context. The effect of this reference
              escaping the context in which it is valid is that the user's
              intended communication will not be able to be understood by the
              recipients of the communication.</t>

              <t>This same problem can also occur when a single user copies a
              name from one context in which it has one meaning, into a
              different context in which it has a different meaning -- for
              example copying a '.onion' Domain Name out of a Tor Browser
              <xref target="TOR"/>, where it has meaning, and pasting this
              name into an ssh client that doesn't support connecting over the
              Tor network.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>We can summarize the advice in this document as follows: <list
              style="symbols">
              <t>Domain Names with unambiguous global meaning are preferable
              to Domain Names with local meaning which will be ambiguous.
              Nevertheless both globally-meaningful and locally-special names
              are in use and must be supported.</t>

              <t>At the time of the writing of this document the IAB was of
              the opinion that there might well be more than one name
              resolution protocol used to resolve Domain Names.</t>
            </list></t>
        </section>

        <section title="Special-Use Domain Names">
          <t>The second important document is <xref target="RFC6761">
          "Special-Use Domain Names"</xref>. RFC 6761 represents the current
          IETF consensus on designating and recording Special-Use Domain
          Names. The IETF has experienced problems with the designation
          process described in RFC 6761; these concerns motivate this
          document. Familiarity with RFC 6761 is a prerequisite for having an
          informed opinion on the topic of Special-Use Domain Names.</t>

          <t>RFC 6761 defines two aspects of Special-Use Domain Names:
          designating a Domain Name to have a special purpose and registering
          that special use in the Special-Use Domain Names registry. The
          designation process is defined in a single sentence (RFC 6761,
          section 4):</t>

          <t><list style="empty">
              <t>If it is determined that special handling of a name is
              required in order to implement some desired new functionality,
              then an IETF "Standards Action" or "IESG Approval" specification
              [RFC5226] MUST be published describing the new
              functionality.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>This sentence requires that any designation of a Special-Use
          Domain Name is subject to the same open review and consensus process
          as used to produce and publish all other IETF specifications.</t>

          <t>The registration process is a purely mechanical process, in which
          the existence of the newly designated Special-Use Domain Name is
          recorded, with a pointer to a section in the relevant specification
          document that defines the ways in which special handling is to be
          applied to the name.</t>

          <t>RFC 6761 provided the process whereby <xref target="RFC6762">
          Multicast DNS</xref> designated ".local" as a Special-Use Domain
          Name and included it in the Special-Use Domain Names registry. It
          itself also enumerated a set of names that had been previously used
          or defined to have special uses prior to the publication of RFC
          6761. Since there had been no registry for these names prior to the
          publication of RFC 6761, the documents defining these names could
          not have added them to the registry.</t>

          <t>There are at least several important points to think of with
          respect to the RFC 6761: <list style="symbols">
              <t>A Special-Use Domain Name may be a name that should be
              resolved using the DNS protocol with no special handling. An
              example of this is 'IN-ADDR.ARPA.' (which is an example of a
              Special-Use Domain Name that is not a TLD).</t>

              <t>A Special-Use Domain Name may be a name that is resolved
              using the DNS protocol, requires no special handling in the stub
              resolver, but requires special handling in the recursive
              resolver. An example of this would be "10.in-addr.arpa."</t>

              <t>A Special-Use Domain Name may be a name that requires special
              handling in the stub resolver. An example would be a Special-Use
              Top-Level Domain Name like '.local' which acts as a signal to
              indicate that the local stub resolver should use a non-DNS
              protocol for name resolution.</t>

              <t>The current IETF consensus (from a process perspective, not
              necessarily from the perspective of what would be consensus if
              the IETF were to attempt to produce a new consensus document) is
              that all of these purposes for Special-Use Domain Names are
              valid.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>The term "stub resolver" in this case does not mean "DNS protocol
          stub resolver." The stub resolver is the entity within a particular
          software stack that takes a question about a Domain Name and answers
          it. One way a stub resolver can answer such a question is using the
          DNS protocol, but it is in the stub resolver, as we are using the
          term here, that the decision as to whether to use a protocol, and if
          so which protocol, or whether to use a local database of some sort,
          is made.</t>

          <t>RFC 6761 does not limit Special-Use Domain Names to TLDs.
          However, at present, all Special-Use Domain Names registered in the
          <xref target="SDO-IANA-SUDR"> IANA Special-Use Domain Names
          registry</xref> are either intended to be resolved using the DNS
          protocol, or are TLDs, or both. That is, at present there exist no
          Special-Use Domain Names which require special handling by stub
          resolvers and which are not at the top level of the naming
          hierarchy.</t>

          <t>One point to take from this is that there is already a
          requirement in RFC 6762 that when a stub resolver encounters the
          special label, '.LOCAL' at the top level of a domain name, it can
          only use the mDNS protocol to resolve that Domain Name.</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="MoU"
                 title="MoU Concerning the Technical Work of the IANA">
          <t>There exists a Memorandum of Understanding (MOU) <xref
          target="RFC2860"/> between the IETF and ICANN (Internet Corporation
          for Assigned Names and Numbers) which discusses how names and
          numbers will be managed through the IANA (Internet Assigned Numbers
          Authority). This document is important to the discussion of
          Special-Use Domain Names because, while it delegates authority for
          managing the Domain Name System Namespace generally to ICANN, it
          reserves to the IETF the authority that RFC 6761 formalizes: <list
              style="empty">
              <t>Note that (a) assignments of Domain Names for technical uses
              (such as Domain Names for inverse DNS lookup), (b) assignments
              of specialised address blocks (such as multicast or anycast
              blocks), and (c) experimental assignments are not considered to
              be policy issues, and shall remain subject to the provisions of
              this Section 4.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>The above text is an addendum to the following: <list
              style="empty">
              <t>Two particular assigned spaces present policy issues in
              addition to the technical considerations specified by the IETF:
              the assignment of Domain Names, and the assignment of IP address
              blocks. These policy issues are outside the scope of this
              MOU.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>In general, then, the assignment of names in the DNS root zone,
          and the management of the DNS namespace, is a function that is
          performed by ICANN. However, the MoU specifically exempts domain
          names assigned for technical use, and uses the example of domains
          used for inverse DNS lookup. Both 'IN-ADDR.ARPA' and 'IP6.ARPA' are
          in the Special-Use Domain Names registry.</t>

          <t>Implicit in the MoU is the fact that the IETF and ICANN retain,
          between them, sole authority for assigning any names from the Domain
          Namespace. Both the IETF and ICANN have internal processes for
          making such assignments.</t>

          <t>The point here is not to say what the implications of this
          statement in the MoU are, but rather to call the reader's attention
          to the existence of this statement.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Liaison Statement on Technical Use of Domain       Names">
          <t>When the IETF received processing requests to add names to the
          Special-Use Domain Name registry, as documented in <xref
          target="I-D.chapin-additional-reserved-tlds"/> and <xref
          target="I-D.grothoff-iesg-special-use-p2p-names"/>, the IETF
          chartered a review of the process defined in RFC 6761 for adding
          names to the registry (as explained earlier). The IETF sent a
          Liaison Statement <xref target="SDO-IAB-ICANN-LS"/> to ICANN to
          notify ICANN of the review, affirm that the discussion would be
          "open and transparent to participation by interested parties" and
          explicitly invite members of the ICANN community to participate.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section anchor="su_sec_docs"
               title="Secondary documents relating to the Special-Use         Domain Name question">
        <t>In addition to these documents, there are several others with which
        participants in this discussion should be familiar.</t>

        <section title="Multicast DNS">
          <t>Multicast DNS <xref target="RFC6762"/> defines the Multicast DNS
          protocol, which uses the '.LOCAL' Special-Use Top-Level Domain Name.
          Section 3 describes the semantics of "multicast DNS names." It is of
          considerable historical importance to note that the -00 version of
          this document, an individual submission, was published in July of
          2001. This version contains substantially the same text in section
          3, and was discussed in the DNSEXT working group at IETF 51 in
          August of 2001<xref target="IETF-PRO-51"/>. The first version of
          this document designated '.LOCAL.ARPA' as the Special-Use Domain
          Name. This idea was strongly opposed by DNSEXT working group
          participants, and as a result the author eventually switched to
          using '.LOCAL'.</t>

          <t>The history of RFC 6762 is documented in substantial detail in
          Appendix H of RFC 6762; some notable milestones include the initial
          proposal to replace Appletalk's NBP in July 1997, the chartering of
          the Zeroconf working group in September 1999, assignment of a
          multicast address for link-local name discovery in April of 2000. A
          companion requirements document, eventually published as <xref
          target="RFC6760"/> was first published in September of 2001.</t>

          <t>The point of mentioning these dates is so that discussions
          involving the time when the '.LOCAL' domain was first deployed, and
          the context in which it was deployed, may be properly informed.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="The .onion Special-Use Top-Level Domain Name">
          <t><xref target="RFC7686">The .onion Special-Use Top-Level Domain
          Name</xref> is important because it is the most recent IETF action
          on the topic of Special-Use Domain Names; although it does not set
          new policy, the mere fact of its publication is worth thinking
          about.</t>

          <t>Two important points to consider about this document are that:
          <list style="symbols">
              <t>The IETF gained consensus to publish it</t>

              <t>Devising a resolution to the situation was constrained by at
              least two factors. First, there was no process for allocating
              special-use domain names at the time that the .onion project
              started using the name, and since at the time the scope of use
              of the name was expected to be very constrained, the developers
              chose to allocate it unilaterally rather than asking the IETF or
              some other SDO to create a new process. <vspace blankLines="1"/>
              Second, for some time, the <xref target="SDO-CABF">CA/Browser
              Forum</xref> had been issuing certificates for what they
              referred to as "internal names." Internal names are names
              allocated unilaterally for use in site-specific contexts.
              Issuing certificates for such names came to be considered
              problematic, since no formal process for testing the validity of
              such names existed. Consequently, CA/Browser Forum decided to
              phase out the use of such names in certificates <xref
              target="SDO-CABF-INT"/>, and set a deadline after which no new
              certificates for such names would be issued <xref
              target="SDO-CABF-DEADLINE"/>. Because the .onion domain was
              allocated unilaterally, this would mean that certificates for
              subdomains of .onion could no longer be issued.<vspace
              blankLines="1"/> The IETF's designation of .onion as a
              Special-Use Top-Level Domain Name was needed to facilitate the
              development of a certificate issuance process specific to .onion
              domain names <xref target="SDO-CABF-BALLOT144"/>.</t>
            </list></t>
        </section>

        <section title="Locally Served DNS Zones">
          <t><xref target="RFC6303">Locally Served DNS Zones</xref> describes
          a particular use case for zones that exist by definition, and that
          are resolved using the DNS protocol, but that cannot have a global
          meaning, because the host IP addresses they reference are not
          unique. This applies to a variety of addresses, including <xref
          target="RFC1918"> Private IPv4 addresses</xref>, <xref
          target="RFC4193">Unique Local IPv6 Unicast Addresses</xref> (in
          which this practice was first described) and <xref
          target="RFC6598">IANA-Reserved IPv4 Prefix for Shared Address
          Space</xref>.</t>

          <t>This use case is distinct from the use-case for Special-Use
          Domain Names like '.local' and '.onion' in that the names are
          resolved using the DNS protocol (but do require extensions or
          exceptions to the usual DNS resolution to enforce resolution in a
          local context rather than the global DNS context). But it shares the
          problem that such names cannot be assumed either to be unique or to
          be functional in all contexts for all Internet-connected hosts.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Name Collision in the DNS">
          <t><xref target="SDO-ICANN-COLL">Name Collision in the DNS</xref> is
          a study commissioned by ICANN that attempts to characterize the
          potential risk to the Internet of adding global DNS delegations for
          names that were not previously delegated in the DNS, not reserved
          under any RFC, but also known to be (.home) or surmised to be
          (.corp) in significant use for Special-Use-type reasons (local scope
          DNS, or other resolution protocols altogether).</t>
        </section>

        <section title="SSAC Advisory on the Stability of the Domain    Namespace">
          <t>ICANN SSAC (<xref target="SDO-ICANN-SSAC"/>) Advisory on the
          Stability of the Domain Namespace <xref target="SDO-ICANN-SAC090"/>
          reports on some issues surrounding the conflicting uses, interested
          parties and processes related to the Domain Namespace. The document
          recommends the development of collaborative processes among the
          various interested parties to coordinate their activities related to
          the Domain Namespace.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Discovery of the IPv6 Prefix Used for IPv6 Address Synthesis">
          <t><xref target="RFC7050">Discovery of the IPv6 Prefix Used for IPv6
          Address Synthesis</xref> is an example of a document that
          successfully used the RFC 6761 process to designate '.ipv4only.arpa'
          as a Special-Use Domain Name; in this case the process worked
          smoothly and without controversy.</t>

          <t>Unfortunately, while the IETF process worked smoothly, in the
          sense that there was little controversy or delay in approving the
          new use, it did not work correctly: the name "ipv4only.arpa" was
          never added to the Special-Use Domain Names registry. This appears
          to have happened because the document did not explicitly request the
          addition of an entry for "ipv4only.arpa" in the SUDN registry. This
          is an illustration of one of the problems that we have with the 6761
          process: it is apparently fairly easy to miss the step of adding the
          name to the registry.</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="addl-tlds"
                 title="Additional Reserved Top Level Domains">
          <t><xref target="I-D.chapin-additional-reserved-tlds"> Additional
          Reserved Top Level Domains</xref> is an example of a document that
          attempted to reserve several TLDs identified by ICANN as
          particularly at risk for collision as Special-Use Domain Names with
          no documented use. This attempt failed.</t>

          <t>Although this document failed to gain consensus to publish, the
          need it was intended to fill still exists. Unfortunately, although a
          fair amount is known about the use of these names, no RFC documents
          how they are used, and why it would be a problem to delegate them.
          Additionally, to the extent that the uses being made of these names
          are valid, no document exists indicating when it might make sense to
          use them, and when it would not make sense to use them.</t>

          <t>RFC 7788 <xref target="RFC7788"/> defines the Domain Name TLD
          ".home" for use as the default name for name resolution relative to
          a home network context. Although, as defined in RFC 7788, ".home" is
          a Special-Use Domain Name, RFC 7788 did not follow the process
          specified in RFC 6761: it did not request that ".home" be added to
          the IANA Special-Use Domain Name registry. This was recognized as a
          mistake, and resulted in the publication of an errata, <xref
          target="ERRATA-4677"/>. Additionally, ".home" is an example of an
          attempt to reuse a Domain Name that has already been put into use
          for other purposes without following established processes<xref
          target="SDO-ICANN-COLL"/>, which further complicates the situation.
          At the time this document was written, the IETF was developing a
          solution to this problem.</t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="History">
      <t>Newcomers to the problem of resolving Domain Names may be under the
      mistaken impression that the DNS sprang, as in the Greek legend of
      Athena, directly from Paul Mockapetris' forehead. This is not the case.
      At the time of the writing of the IAB technical document, memories would
      have been fresh of the evolutionary process that led to the DNS'
      dominance as a protocol for Domain Name resolution.</t>

      <t>In fact, in the early days of the Internet, hostnames were resolved
      using a text file, HOSTS.TXT, which was maintained by a central
      authority, the Network Information Center, and distributed to all hosts
      on the Internet using the <xref target="RFC0959">File Transfer Protocol
      (FTP)</xref>. The inefficiency of this process is cited as a reason for
      the development of <xref target="RFC0882">the DNS</xref> <xref
      target="RFC0883"/> in 1983.</t>

      <t>However, the transition from HOSTS.TXT to the DNS was not smooth. For
      example, <xref target="CORP-SUN-NIS">Sun Microsystems's Network
      Information System</xref>, at the time known as Yellow Pages, was an
      active competitor to the DNS, although it failed to provide a complete
      solution to the global naming problem.</t>

      <t>Another example was NetBIOS Name Service, also known as WINS <xref
      target="RFC1002"/>. This protocol was used mostly by Microsoft Windows
      machines, but also by open source BSD and Linux operating systems to do
      name resolution using Microsoft's own name resolution protocol.</t>

      <t>Most modern operating systems can still use the '/etc/hosts' file for
      name resolution. Many still have a name service switch that can be
      configured on the host to resolve some domains using NIS or WINS. Most
      have the capability to resolve names using mDNS by recognizing the
      special meaning of the '.local' Special-Use Top Level Domain Name.</t>

      <t>The Sun Microsystems model of having private domains within a
      corporate site, while supporting the global Domain Name system for
      off-site, persisted even after the NIS protocol fell into disuse.
      Microsoft used to recommend that site administrators use a "private" TLD
      for internal use, and this practice was very much a part of the
      zeitgeist at the time (see section 5.1 of <xref
      target="SDO-ICANN-COLL"/> and Appendix G of <xref target="RFC6762"/>).
      This attitude is at the root of the widespread practice of simply
      picking an apparently-unused TLD and using it for experimental purposes,
      which persists even at the time of writing of this memo.</t>

      <t>This history is being presented because discussions about Special-Use
      Domain Names in the IETF often come down to the question of why users of
      new name resolution protocols choose to use Domain Names, rather than
      using some other naming concept that doesn't overlap with the namespace
      that, in modern times is, by default, resolved using the DNS.</t>

      <t>The answer is that as a consequence of this long history of resolving
      Domain Names using a wide variety of name resolution systems, Domain
      Names are required in a large variety of contexts in user interfaces and
      applications programming interfaces. Any name that appears in such a
      context is a Domain Name. So developers of new name resolution systems
      that must work in existing contexts actually have no choice: they must
      use a Special-Use Domain Name to segregate a portion of the namespace
      for use with their system.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>This document mentions various security and privacy considerations in
      the text. However, this document creates no new security or privacy
      concerns.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA considerations">
      <t>This document has no actions for IANA.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Contributors">
      <t>Mark Andrews, Stuart Cheshire, David Conrad, Paul Ebersman, Aaron
      Falk and Suzanne Woolf all made helpful and insightful observations or
      patiently answered questions. This should not be taken as an indication
      that any of these folks actually agree with what the document says, but
      their generosity with time and thought are appreciated in any case.</t>

      <t>Stephane Bortzmeyer, John Dickinson, Bob Harold, Paul Hoffman, Russ
      Housley, Joel Jaeggli, Andrew McConachie, George Michaelson, Petr Spacek
      and others provided significant review and / or useful comments.</t>

      <t>This document also owes a great deal to Ed Lewis' excellent work on
      <xref target="I-D.lewis-domain-names">what a "Domain Name"
      is</xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="RFC Editor Considerations">
      <t>The authors were unable to find dates for references <xref
      target="SDO-CABF-DEADLINE"/> and <xref target="SDO-CABF"/>. Please fix
      up those references as appropriate (and remove this section before
      publication).</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.0882" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.0883" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.0959" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.1002" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.1034" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.1035" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.1918" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2352" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2826" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2860" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4193" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6303" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6598" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6760" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6761" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6762" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7050" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7686" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7719" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7788" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.chapin-additional-reserved-tlds" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.grothoff-iesg-special-use-p2p-names" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.lewis-domain-names" ?>

      <reference anchor="SDO-CABF-INT"
                 target="https://www.digicert.com/internal-names.htm">
        <front>
          <title>Guidance on the Deprecation of Internal Server Names and
          Reserved IP Addresses</title>

          <author>
            <organization>CA/Browser Forum</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="June" year="2012"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="SDO-CABF-DEADLINE"
                 target="https://www.digicert.com/internal-names.htm">
        <front>
          <title>SSL Certificates for Internal Server Names</title>

          <author>
            <organization>CA/Browser Forum</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="???" year="????"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="SDO-CABF" target="https://cabforum.org">
        <front>
          <title>CA/Browser Forum</title>

          <author>
            <organization>CA/Browser Forum</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="???" year="????"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="SDO-CABF-BALLOT144"
                 target="https://cabforum.org/2015/02/18/ballot-144-validation-rules-dot-onion-names">
        <front>
          <title>Ballot 144 - Validation Rules for .onion Names</title>

          <author>
            <organization>CA/Browser Forum</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="February" year="2015"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="SDO-ICANN-COLL"
                 target="https://www.icann.org/en/system/files/files/name-collision-02aug13-en.pdf">
        <front>
          <title>Name Collisions in the DNS</title>

          <author>
            <organization>Interisle Consulting Group, LLC</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="August" year="2013"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="SDO-ICANN-SAC090"
                 target="https://www.icann.org/en/system/files/files/sac-090-en.pdf">
        <front>
          <title>SSAC Advisory on the Stability of the Domain
          Namespace</title>

          <author>
            <organization>ICANN Security and Stability Advisory
            Committee</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="December" year="2016"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="SDO-ICANN-SSAC"
                 target="https://www.icann.org/groups/ssac">
        <front>
          <title>SSAC Advisory on the Stability of the Domain
          Namespace</title>

          <author>
            <organization>ICANN Security and Stability Advisory
            Committee</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="December" year="2016"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="SDO-IANA-SUDR"
                 target="http://www.iana.org/assignments/special-use-domain-names/special-use-domain-names.xhtml">
        <front>
          <title>Special-Use Domain Names registry</title>

          <author>
            <organization>Internet Assigned Numbers Authority</organization>
          </author>

          <date day="27" month="October" year="2015"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="SDO-ICANN-DAG"
                 target="https://newgtlds.icann.org/en/applicants/agb/guidebook-full-04jun12-en.pdf">
        <front>
          <title>Special-Use Domain Names registry</title>

          <author>
            <organization>Internet Assigned Numbers Authority</organization>
          </author>

          <date day="27" month="October" year="2015"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="SDO-IAB-ICANN-LS"
                 target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/liaison/1351">
        <front>
          <title>Liaison Statement from the IAB to the ICANN Board on
          Technical Use of Domain Names</title>

          <author>
            <organization>Internet Architecture Board</organization>
          </author>

          <date day="15" month="September" year="2015"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="ERRATA-4677"
                 target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/errata/eid4677">
        <front>
          <title>Errata ID: 4677 (RFC7788)</title>

          <author>
            <organization>Internet Architecture Board</organization>
          </author>

          <date day="" month="April" year="2016"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="CORP-SUN-NIS">
        <front>
          <title>Large System and Network Administration</title>

          <author>
            <organization>Sun Microsystems</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="March" year="1990"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="IETF-PRO-51"
                 target="http://www.ietf.org/proceedings/51/51-45.htm#TopOfPage">
        <front>
          <title>Proceedings of the 51st IETF</title>

          <author>
            <organization>Internet Engineering Task Force</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="August" year="2001"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="TOR" target="https://www.torproject.org">
        <front>
          <title>Tor</title>

          <author>
            <organization>The Tor Project</organization>
          </author>

          <date year="2017"/>
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>

    <section title="Change Log.">
      <t>-06 to -07:<list style="symbols">
          <t>Issue #88: Bulleted list should be numbered, not unordered -
          Updated the list of problems to be numbered, instead of unordered.
          This is to allow future documents to refer to specific issues.</t>

          <t>Misc: Removed duplicate word ("that that" -&gt; "that")</t>

          <t>Backfilled the "Change Log" to reflect the issues addressed
          between Version -05 and -06.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>-05 to -06:<list style="symbols">
          <t>Issue #87: Section 4.2.2: expand "certs" to "certificates"</t>

          <t>Issue #86: Stephane Bortzmeyer: lying DNS resolvers</t>

          <t>Issue #85: Stephane Bortzmeyer: unilateral use</t>

          <t>Issue #84: Stephane Bortzmeyer: Use of the registry is
          inconsistent</t>

          <t>Issue #83: Stephane Bortzmeyer: IETF-ICANN have a liaison
          relationship</t>

          <t>Issue #82: Bob Harold: extra "be used"</t>

          <t>Issue #81: Editorial changes from Benoit Claise AD review</t>

          <t>Issue #80: Section 3 - Clarify citation of SDO-ICANN-COLL</t>

          <t>Issue #79: Update reference to "Special-Use Domain Names
          registry" (?)</t>

          <t>Issue #78: Section 4.2.7 - add citation of Errata correcting use
          of ".home" in RFC 7788</t>

          <t>Issue #77: Section 2 - correct citation of definition of gTLD</t>

          <t>Issue #76: Section 3 - clarify that problems are listed
          regardless of validity or ownership,</t>

          <t>Issue #74, #75: Meaning versus binding (Andrew McConachie),
          global/local (Andrew McConachie)</t>

          <t>Issue #73: Editorial improvements, Section 4.2.7</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>-03 to -04:<list style="symbols">
          <t>Issue #72: Corrected original text to reflect that RFC 7050
          neglected to request an SUDN registry entry for "ipv4only.arpa", but
          any inference about the cause for the oversight would be
          speculation.</t>

          <t>Issue #69: Edited Joel's suggested text.</t>

          <t>Issue #67: Minor change to Joel's suggested text.</t>

          <t>Issue #66: Edited second text update suggested by Joel and
          reverted third change back to the original text.</t>

          <t>Issue #64: Minor changes to text suggested by Joel.</t>

          <t>Issue #61: Minor edit based on authors' consensus in response to
          Joel's comment.</t>

          <t>Addressed Joel / Benoit's AD comments. See GH issues</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>-02 to -03 (in Github): <list style="symbols">
          <t>Passes idnits except for errors resulting from a reference to an
          RFC 2119 keyword and a citation of RFC 5226 with no matching
          reference in quoted text at line 493.</t>

          <t>Issue #60: Add new section "6. Summary" -- Petr Spacek
          https://github.com/Abhayakara/draft-tldr-sutld-ps/issues/60</t>

          <t>Issue #57: Document needs an "Security Considerations" section
          https://github.com/Abhayakara/draft-tldr-sutld-ps/issues/57</t>

          <t>Numerous editorial changes for consistency; e.g. use "Special-Use
          Domain Names" throughout.</t>

          <t>Issue #58: Document needs an "IANA Considerations" section
          https://github.com/Abhayakara/draft-tldr-sutld-ps/issues/58</t>

          <t>Issue #39: Overlapping bullets in Section 3, with proposed
          restructuring -- Russ Housley
          https://github.com/Abhayakara/draft-tldr-sutld-ps/issues/39</t>

          <t>Issue #55: Editorial improvement to Section 3 (4) -- John
          Dickinson
          https://github.com/Abhayakara/draft-tldr-sutld-ps/issues/55</t>

          <t>Issue #34: Separate two problems in paragraph that begins "No
          mechanism exists for adding a name to the registry...." (2 issues)
          -- Suzanne Woolf
          https://github.com/Abhayakara/draft-tldr-sutld-ps/issues/34</t>

          <t>Issue #52: Editorial improvement to Section 3 (1) -- John
          Dickinson
          https://github.com/Abhayakara/draft-tldr-sutld-ps/issues/52</t>

          <t>Issue #51: Clarification in Introduction -- John Dickinson
          https://github.com/Abhayakara/draft-tldr-sutld-ps/issues/51</t>

          <t>Issue #49: Should cite https://datatracker.ietf.org/liaison/1351
          -- George Michaelson
          https://github.com/Abhayakara/draft-tldr-sutld-ps/issues/49</t>

          <t>Issue #50: IETF precedence in Special-Use names registry -- Ted
          Lemon
          https://github.com/Abhayakara/draft-tldr-sutld-ps/issues/50</t>

          <t>Issue #48: 4.1.2 cites sub-domains of .ARPA arguing for special
          use TLD -- George Michaelson
          https://github.com/Abhayakara/draft-tldr-sutld-ps/issues/48</t>

          <t>Issue #47: 4.3 should be made more prominent -- George Michaelson
          https://github.com/Abhayakara/draft-tldr-sutld-ps/issues/47</t>

          <t>Issue #43: Spell out SUDN and SUTLDN rather than use acronyms --
          Russ Housley
          https://github.com/Abhayakara/draft-tldr-sutld-ps/issues/43</t>

          <t>Issue #41: Reword bullet in Section 3 regarding Domain Name TLDs
          that have been commandeered, as reported in SDO-ICANN-COLL -- Russ
          Housley
          https://github.com/Abhayakara/draft-tldr-sutld-ps/issues/41</t>

          <t>Issue #40: Note that time to publish spec for .local included
          inventing SUDN registry -- Russ Housley
          https://github.com/Abhayakara/draft-tldr-sutld-ps/issues/41</t>

          <t>Issue #37: Title should be "Special-Use Domain Names Problem
          Statement" -- Russ Housley
          https://github.com/Abhayakara/draft-tldr-sutld-ps/issues/37</t>

          <t>Issue #36: Expand on desire for Special-Use names to be
          human-readable -- Suzanne Woolf
          https://github.com/Abhayakara/draft-tldr-sutld-ps/issues/36</t>

          <t>Issue #35: Clarify "No process exists [...]" to include both IETF
          process and other process -- Suzanne Woolf
          https://github.com/Abhayakara/draft-tldr-sutld-ps/issues/35</t>

          <t>Issue #31: Add justification for concern about IETF's ability to
          assign names for technical use -- Suzanne Woolf
          https://github.com/Abhayakara/draft-tldr-sutld-ps/issues/31</t>

          <t>Issue #12: Add DNSSEC to text -- John Levine
          https://github.com/Abhayakara/draft-tldr-sutld-ps/issues/12</t>

          <t>Issue #6: Without a process, we just have chaos -- Stuart
          Cheshire
          https://github.com/Abhayakara/draft-tldr-sutld-ps/issues/6</t>

          <t>Issue #32: Have assignments through RFC 6761 really had
          "technical mistakes"? -- Suzanne Wolff
          https://github.com/Abhayakara/draft-tldr-sutld-ps/issues/32</t>

          <t>Issue #29: Add a reason to bypass external process: expectation
          for use of new name to be restricted to local scope -- Suzanne Wolff
          https://github.com/Abhayakara/draft-tldr-sutld-ps/issues/29</t>

          <t>Issue #27: Is "technical use" really ambiguous; too inclusive for
          some people and too limited for others -- Suzanne Wolff
          https://github.com/Abhayakara/draft-tldr-sutld-ps/issues/27</t>

          <t>Issue #24: Replacement for "commandeer" (2 issues)-- Suzanne
          Wolff
          https://github.com/Abhayakara/draft-tldr-sutld-ps/issues/24</t>

          <t>Issue #22: Clarify importance of the "root of the Domain
          Namespace" -- Suzanne Wolff
          https://github.com/Abhayakara/draft-tldr-sutld-ps/issues/22</t>

          <t>Issue #21: Section 3 - clarify paragraphs 2 and 3 -- Suzanne
          Wolff
          https://github.com/Abhayakara/draft-tldr-sutld-ps/issues/21</t>

          <t>Issue #20: Section 3: Clarify sentences beginning "Solutions to
          these problems..." -- Suzanne Wolff
          https://github.com/Abhayakara/draft-tldr-sutld-ps/issues/20</t>

          <t>Issue #19: Define "default" or "assumed" use of domain names to
          be within DNS -- Suzanne Wolff
          https://github.com/Abhayakara/draft-tldr-sutld-ps/issues/19</t>

          <t>Issue #18: Cite definition of RFC 7719 and domain names draft in
          definition of "domain name" -- Suzanne Wolff
          https://github.com/Abhayakara/draft-tldr-sutld-ps/issues/18</t>

          <t>Issue #45: Correct usages of Tor Browser and Tor -- Russ Housley
          (https://github.com/Abhayakara/draft-tldr-sutld-ps/issues/45)</t>

          <t>Issue #46: Reformat citation of RFC 2860 -- Russ Housley
          (https://github.com/Abhayakara/draft-tldr-sutld-ps/issues/46)</t>

          <t>Issue #44: Clean up reference to SDO-ICANN-DAG in first bullet in
          section 3 -- Russ Housley
          (https://github.com/Abhayakara/draft-tldr-sutld-ps/issues/44)</t>

          <t>Issue #42: Add reference to SDO-ICANN-SAC090 in section 4.2.5 --
          Russ Housley
          (https://github.com/Abhayakara/draft-tldr-sutld-ps/issues/42)</t>

          <t>Issue #30: Leaked queries aren't an operational problem in
          practice -- Suzanne Wolf
          (https://github.com/Abhayakara/draft-tldr-sutld-ps/issues/30)</t>

          <t>Address some of the simpler issues, including:</t>

          <t>Issue #13: Spelling of Tor -- Jeremy Rand
          (https://github.com/Abhayakara/draft-tldr-sutld-ps/issues/13)</t>

          <t>Issue #14: Change SDO to "organizations" -- Suzanne Woolf
          (https://github.com/Abhayakara/draft-tldr-sutld-ps/issues/14)</t>

          <t>Issue #16: Match number of "policies" and "that policy" --
          Suzanne
          (https://github.com/Abhayakara/draft-tldr-sutld-ps/issues/16)</t>

          <t>Issue #17: Clarify sentence beginning with "In support of the
          particular set of problems described here...." -- Suzanne.
          (https://github.com/Abhayakara/draft-tldr-sutld-ps/issues/14)</t>

          <t>Issue #23: Match number of "names" and "a TLD" -- Suzanne.
          (https://github.com/Abhayakara/draft-tldr-sutld-ps/issues/23)</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>-01 to -02:<list style="symbols">
          <t>Language cleanup from Ted.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>-00 to -01:<list style="symbols">
          <t>Improved the terminology.</t>

          <t>Included reference to SAC090.</t>

          <t>Added ICANN Reserved Names (e.g .icann, .iesg, .arin) to types of
          names.</t>

          <t>Improved background.</t>

          <t>Noted that semantics may differ between resolution contexts.</t>

          <t>Pointer to .home / .corp / .mail, other "toxic" names</t>

          <t>Readability fixes.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>-04 to ietf-00<list style="symbols">
          <t>Document adopted by WG.</t>

          <t>Significant changes from CfA integrated, please refer to
          diff.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>-03 to -04:<list style="symbols">
          <t>Replaced 'Internet Names' with 'Domain Names' - suggestion by
          John Levine.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>-02 to -03:<list style="symbols">
          <t>Readability fixes, small grammar updates.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>-01 to -02:<list style="symbols">
          <t>Cleaned up the abstract.</t>

          <t>Fixed the case of Internet</t>

          <t>Reference to Ed Lewis' "Domain Names"</t>

          <t>Fleshed out the problems, primarily the coordination, collisions
          ones.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>-00 to -01:<list style="symbols">
          <t>Large refactoring, basically a rewrite. Incorporated comments,
          removed a bunch of unneeded text, etc.</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
